[{"category":"","question":"What are the symptoms?","answer":"<p>Initial symptoms include fever, intense weakness, muscle pain, headache and sore throat. These symptoms are followed by vomiting, diarrhea, rash, impaired kidney and liver function and sometimes internal and external bleeding. </p>\n\n<p>Symptoms usually appear 8-10 days after infection. Lab tests of contaminated individuals find low white blood cell and platelet counts.</p>","link":"http://www.usatoday.com/story/news/nation-now/2014/10/15/ebola-flu-symptoms-sick/17309147/","timestamp":"9 a.m. EDT November 17, 2014","rowNumber":1},{"category":"","question":"How does Ebola spread?","answer":"<p>Ebola is <b>not</b> airborne. The virus can be spread through direct contact with the bodily fluids of an infected person -- urine, saliva, sweat, feces, vomit, breast milk and semen, for example -- or a contaminated needle.</p>","link":"http://www.usatoday.com/story/news/nation/2014/10/06/how-ebola-spreads/16802063/","timestamp":"","rowNumber":2},{"category":"","question":"How likely am I to contract Ebola?","answer":"<p>You’re <b>highly unlikely</b> to contract Ebola -- unless you’ve been in direct contact with an infected person while he or she is exhibiting symptoms. Health care workers of patients in advanced stages of the disease are at the highest risk of contracting Ebola.</p>\n\n<p>Ebola is not easily spread during the early phases of the disease, when patients are still healthy enough to walk around. The family of Ebola patient Thomas Eric Duncan, for example, shared a small apartment with him but did not get Ebola.</p>","link":"http://www.usatoday.com/story/news/nation/2014/10/14/ebola-spreads-easily-hospitals/17247157/","timestamp":"","rowNumber":3},{"category":"","question":"What is the treatment?","answer":"<p>There is no vaccine, although two are being tested.</p>\n\n<p>Although there are no proven therapies, several experimental ones are being developed. A handful of Ebola patients received these experimental drugs, although supplies of one have been exhausted and supplies of another are very low.</p>\n\n<p>Some patients have gotten blood transfusions from Ebola survivors in the hope that a survivor's antibodies will help a sick person's immune system fight off the virus.</p>\n","link":"http://www.usatoday.com/story/news/nation/2014/10/14/more-ebola-vaccine-studies/17254175/","timestamp":"","rowNumber":4},{"category":"","question":"Why is Ebola in the news?","answer":"<p>This is the worst outbreak in history.  There have been more than 14,413 Ebola cases in eight countries and 5,177 reported deaths, as of Nov. 14,  according to the World Health Organization.</p>\n\n<p>The vast majority are from West Africa, specifically Liberia, Guinea and Sierra Leone. Two people have died in the USA.</p>","link":"http://www.usatoday.com/story/news/nation-now/2014/10/24/map-ebola-virus-outbreaks-worldwide/17823591/","timestamp":"","rowNumber":5},{"category":"","question":"How did the outbreak get so bad?","answer":"<p>The hardest-hit regions -- Liberia, Guinea and Sierra Leone -- are among the poorest\n in the world. </p>\n\n<p>Unlike in the USA, there aren’t enough or adequate medical personnel, facilities and gear. For example, Liberia had only 51 doctors for a country of 4.3 million people  before the outbreak began. Patients have been turned away from hospitals too full to accept them.</p>\n\n<p>Although the first case occurred in December in Guinea, health officials didn’t realize they were dealing with an Ebola outbreak until March, when there were nearly 50 cases.</p>\n\n<p>Decades of political instability and civil wars in West Africa have fueled mistrust of government officials who have tried to educate residents about the outbreak. Rumors about outsiders bringing the virus into communities exacerbate the situation. In Guinea, eight people, including  health workers, were abducted and murdered in September.</p>\n\n<p>The tradition of kissing or touching a corpse during funeral rites helps spread the virus.</p>","link":"http://www.usatoday.com/story/news/nation-now/2014/10/01/ebola-outbreak-unlikely-in-united-states/16527211/","timestamp":"","rowNumber":6},{"category":"","question":"How deadly is Ebola?","answer":"<p>The outbreak has a mortality rate of about 70%. In past Ebola outbreaks, mortality rates have varied from 25% to 90%, according to the World Health Organization. </p>\n\n<p>Transmission is very difficult in the early stages of the disease. The average Ebola patient in Africa transmits the virus to 1-2 people. In comparison, people with measles spread the disease to 12 to 18 other people, according to the Michigan Center for Public Health Preparedness. </p>","link":"http://www.usatoday.com/story/news/nation/2014/10/01/comparing-ebola-flu/16554689/","timestamp":"","rowNumber":7},{"category":"","question":"How did Ebola spread to humans?","answer":"<p>The first Ebola patient probably contracted the virus from an infected animal.</p>\n\n<p>Fruit bats in Africa are the natural host. There’s no evidence that North American bats carry Ebola.</p>","link":"http://www.cdc.gov/vhf/ebola/transmission/qas-pets.html","timestamp":"","rowNumber":8},{"category":"","question":"Who's been treated in the USA?","answer":"<p>Two people of the 10 people who were treated for Ebola in the USA have died. Martin Salia, a surgeon treating Ebola patients in his home country of Sierra Leone, died Nov. 17 at the Nebraska Medical Center. On Oct. 8, Thomas Eric Duncan, who had traveled from Liberia, died on Oct. 8. </p>\n<p>The others have recovered.</p>\n\n ","link":"http://www.usatoday.com/story/news/nation/2014/10/23/ebola-in-nyc-the-answer-will-be-here-in-12-hours/17786777/","timestamp":"","rowNumber":9},{"category":"","question":"How has the U.S. government responded?","answer":"<p>The U.S. military is prepared to provide up to 3,000 troops to help with the Ebola outbreak in Africa. </p>\n\n<p>Hundreds of troops in Liberia are building treatment centers and training locals on how to handle Ebola patients. U.S. forces are not treating patients directly.</p>\n\n<p>On Oct. 16, President Obama signed an order allowing reservists to be called into active duty to support the Ebola effort.</p>\n\n<p>Obama named an Ebola czar, Ron Klain, to coordinate efforts to contain Ebola.</p>\n","link":"http://www.usatoday.com/story/news/world/2014/10/17/ebola-military-pentagon-reservists-liberia/17426929/","timestamp":"","rowNumber":10},{"category":"","question":"What are the changes to flight screenings?","answer":"<p>Travelers from West Africa arriving at five U.S. airports will have their temperature taken and face questions about their health in an effort to prevent the spread of Ebola.</p>\n\n<p>The airports are: Atlanta, Chicago O'Hare, New York JFK, Newark Liberty and Washington Dulles. </p>\n\n<p>The screening entails taking the passenger’s temperature with a non-contact thermometer and answering questions about possible exposure to Ebola.</p>","link":"http://www.usatoday.com/story/todayinthesky/2014/10/08/ebola-and-air-travel-what-to-expect/16923229/","timestamp":"","rowNumber":11},{"category":"","question":"Can I catch Ebola by touching a bowling ball?","answer":"<p>U.S. Ebola patient Craig Spencer went to a bowling alley after contracting Ebola in Liberia. If Spencer touched a bowling ball with his sweaty palms, and you then touched his sweat on the ball -- could you get Ebola?</p>\n\n<p>It’s highly unlikely.</p>\n\n<p>Ebola is not easily spread during the early phases of the disease, when patients are still healthy enough to walk around. </p>\n\n<p>The virus can be spread through direct contact with the bodily fluids, including sweat, urine, saliva, feces, vomit, breast milk and semen, for example. Direct contact means the body fluid had to touch an open cut on your skin or your eyes, nose or mouth.</p>","link":"","timestamp":"","rowNumber":12},{"category":"","question":"Will Ebola Mutate to Become Airborne? ","answer":"<p>Ebola is not airborne, but could it change its mode of transmission?</p>\n\n<p>Nope, says the World Health Organization.</p>\n\n<p>“Speculation that Ebola virus disease might mutate into a form that could easily spread among humans through the air is just that: speculation, unsubstantiated by any evidence,” according to a statement Oct. 6 from the WHO.</p>","link":"","timestamp":"","rowNumber":13},{"category":"","question":"How likely is an outbreak in the USA?","answer":"<p>Now that there are Ebola cases in the USA, we are on the verge of a widespread, \"Contagion\"-style outbreak, right? </p>\n\n<p>Chances are close to zero, federal health officials say.</p>\n\n<p>Unlike West Africa, where the outbreak is occurring, the USA has the best health system in the world, including isolation wards, personnel and gear that protects against the spread of Ebola.</p>\n\n<p>The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention has protocols in place for health workers, from what doctors and nurses need to wear when treating an Ebola patient to how to prepare a body to be moved to the morgue.</p>","link":"http://www.usatoday.com/story/news/nation-now/2014/10/13/ebola-virus-protocol-health-workers/17181873/","timestamp":"","rowNumber":14},{"category":"","question":"How do health care workers protect themselves?","answer":"<p>According to updated guidelines from the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, health workers treating Ebola patients should wear personal protective equipment (PPE) to ensure no skin exposure. The PPE includes a respirator, a fluid-resistant gown, a full-face shield, double gloves and boots that reach at least mid-calf. </p>\n \n<p>The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention recommends specific protocols for how to put on and take off this equipment. Hospital staff need extensive training to make sure everyone knows how to protect themselves. Also, a site manager should oversee all aspects of the Ebola unit. </p>","link":"http://www.cdc.gov/media/releases/2014/fs1020-ebola-personal-protective-equipment.html","timestamp":"","rowNumber":15},{"category":"","question":"How is Ebola diagnosed?","answer":"<p>Early symptoms of Ebola are similar to the flu or other diseases, such as fever and muscle pain. But if someone with these symptoms has had contact with an infected person, they should be isolated and tested.</p>\n \n<p>Ebola is diagnosed after lab-confirmed tests, ideally blood samples. The virus can be detected in the blood of an infected person only after symptoms appear, usually fever.</p>","link":"http://www.cdc.gov/vhf/ebola/diagnosis/","timestamp":"","rowNumber":16},{"category":"","question":"Who’s quarantined?","answer":"<p>States, including New Jersey and New York, have introduced tough rules that require aid workers traveling from West Africa to be quarantined for 21 days. The White House and some health care workers have said the measures are overly strict.</p>\n\n<p>For people who have traveled from West Africa, the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention recommends local health care officials monitor for fever twice daily for 21 days. These people must notify officials if they develop a fever or other symptoms. </p>\n\n<p>The CDC also issued interim rules Oct. 27 that recommend high-risk people traveling from West Africa to not use public transportation, work outside of the home or go to public gatherings. The guidance does not require mandatory quarantines. But the CDC has no enforcement authority and state and local authorities can develop their own policies.</p>","link":"http://www.cdc.gov/media/releases/2014/p1022-post-arrival-monitoring.html","timestamp":"","rowNumber":17}]